Guide to the School of Engineering and Applied Science records, 1917-2002 RG0012
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
School of Engineering and Applied Science records
1917-2002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0012
9 Linear Feet
Collection includes financial reports, correspondence, meeting minutes, by-laws, memos, publications, brochures, photos and slides.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from the School of Engineering and Applied Science.
Historical Note
The School of Engineering and Applied Science (SEAS) at The George Washington University was organized on October 1, 1884, as the Corcoran Scientific School of Columbian University, and was situated in the University Building at 15th and H Streets, N.W. The School was named for William W. Corcoran, Trustee and President of the Corporation (as the Board of Trustees was referred to at the time) from 1869-88. Day and evening courses in science and technology were offered, which led to the degrees of Bachelor of Science, Civil Engineer, Mechanical Engineer, and Mining Engineer. Although the school lacked the national distinction that was to come, it was among the first to accept women for degree candidacy in engineering.
In 1903 a single Department of Arts and Sciences was authorized to offer graduate engineering degrees. Administrative changes led to the creation of the Washington College of Engineering in 1905, as one of the several semi-independent undergraduate colleges of the University.
In 1909, the name of the College was changed to the College of Engineering and Mechanic Arts, and the curricula were revised to give the students a thorough understanding of the theory underlying engineering practice. Emphasis was placed on the development of a knowledge of scientific principles upon which the student could build and by which he or she might solve new problems as they were met in practice.
The name of the School was changed in 1914 to the College of Engineering, and later to the School of Engineering. Architecture was dropped from the curriculum and degrees were limited to the field of engineering. However, the primary emphasis upon principles rather than technology, which had characterized the School since 1903, was continued and remain to this day as one of the important distinguishing features of the School.
The School of Engineering and Applied Science's history has been marked by distinguished service to the nation. In 1940, with the nation on the edge of war, the school created seven special courses to prepare the country for the stresses that war would put on America's productive capacity. Topics included concrete testing and map making. By 1944, these courses had evolved into 15-week war-training courses covering such topics as the elements of interior ballistics.
In 1962, the name of the School became the School of Engineering and Applied Science. Through its five departments - Civil and Environmental Engineering; Computer Science; Electrical and Computer Engineering; Engineering Management and Systems Engineering; and Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering - the School of Engineering and Applied Science offers undergraduate study leading to the degrees of Bachelor of Science (with majors in biomedical engineering, civil engineering, computer engineering, computer science, electrical engineering, mechanical engineering, and systems engineering), and Bachelor of Arts (with majors in applied science and technology and in computer science). Five-year bachelor's/master's degree programs are available for selected majors.
In cooperation with the Law School, an integrated engineering and law program leading to the degrees of Bachelor of Science or Arts and Juris Doctor is offered. An integrated engineering and medicine program leading to the degrees of Bachelor of Science or Arts and Doctor of Medicine is offered in cooperation with the School of Medicine and Health Sciences. The School offers graduate study leading to the degrees of Master of Science, Master of Engineering Management, and Doctor of Science and to the professional degrees of Engineer and Applied Scientist. The Dean of the School reports to the Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs.
From 1942-71 and 1980-91 the School published the journal Mecheleciv, and since the early 1960's has sponsored the annual Frank Howard lecture given by the alumni association.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include financial reports, correspondence, meeting minutes, by-laws, memos, publications, brochures, photographs and slides. They range in date from 1917-2002, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Dean of the School of Engineering and Applied Science. Note: Not all series are processed. Ask staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized into eight series: four series of Departmental files, Graphics, Records, Mecheleciv magazine and Publications and Audio Video materials.
Electrical engineering and electronics; Computer engineering; Civil engineering; Reports and studies; Color slides; By-laws; Black-and-white slides; Engineering; Finance; Washington (D.C.); George Washington University; George Washington University. School of Engineering and Applied Science
- Departmental records, 1984; RG0012 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains financial reports, bills, statements, and meeting minutes. These materials are all from the year 1984.
  - Financial Records, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - Financial Statements, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bills, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes and other documents, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Graphics, 1970-1999; RG0012 Series 3; 2 Linear feet (Box 2, Box 1)
  This series contains photographs and color slides. These images date from the 1970s through the 1990s and cover the subject of project work such as concrete canoes.
  - The early years, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The 1990's, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Concrete Canoe Races - Blue Binder, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Concrete Canoes - Narrow binder, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Color slides, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - School of Engineering and Applied Sciences slides, black binder, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Four manila folders containing various photographs from the 1970s to the 1990s, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Departmental files, 1985-1992; RG0012 Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series contains meeting minutes and correspondence. These items date from 1985-92.
- Departmental files, 1962-1982; RG0012 Series 5; 1 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2)
  This series contains meeting notes, by-laws, events, correspondence, treasurers reports, and Frank Howard lectures. These materials date from 1962-82. The meeting notes are from the Board of Directors.
  - Awards, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors Meetings, 1965-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Meetings, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Meetings, Attendance, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Rosters, 1966-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - By-Laws, Operations Manual, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Candidates for Graduation, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Committees, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Directory, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Events, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Finance - Bank Statements [1/2], 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Finance - Bank Statements [2/2], 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Finance - Check Stubs, 1967-1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Finance - Records, 1970-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Finance - Records, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Finance - Treasurer's Reports, 1970-1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Frank Howard Lectures, 1962-1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Purposes, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Records, 1917-2002; RG0012 Series 6; 1.75 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2)
  This series contains correspondence, brochures, reports, admissions applications, yearbooks, an annual, and newsletters from the School of Engineering and Applied Science. They range in date from 1917 to 2002. They concern the College of Engineering, the Architectural Club, admissions, courses, programs, conferences, and meetings.
  - Alumni -- Alumni Association - School of Engineering and Applied Science Alumni Association, 1967-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clubs, Societies, Organizations--Architectural Club, 1917-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- ), 1941-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Admissions, 1962-1995 -- --ca. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Admissions--Recruitment, 1969-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- ) - Center For Measurement Science, 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Civil, Mechanical, and Environmental Engineering (CMEE), 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Continuing Engineering Education, 1969-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Defense Training Program (1940- ), 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- ) - Cooperative Education & Training Program, 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- ) - Electrical Engineering & Computer Science, 1970-1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Engineers' Council, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Engineering Administration, 1968-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Engineering Administration Theses, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Graduate Programs [1/2], 1953-2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Graduate Programs [2/2], 1961-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Graduate Programs Graduate Student Handbook, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Joint Institute For Acoustics & Flight Sciences (JIAFS), 1972-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Off-Campus Programs, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- ) - Operations Research, 1970-1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- ) - Operations Research Symposia, Conferences, Institutes, 1972-1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Promotional Brochures [1/2] (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Promotional Brochures [2/2] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Research, 1971-2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Symposia, Conferences, Institutes, Workshops, Seminars [1/2], 1962-1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Symposia, Conferences, Institutes, Workshops, Seminars [2/2], 1949-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Engineering & Applied Science, School of (1962- )--Undergraduate Programs, 1967-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Mecheleciv magazine, 1942-1990; RG0012 Series 7; 2 Linear feet (Box 2, Box 1A)
  This series contains Mecheleciv magazine They range in date from 1942-1990.
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 07/1942 --05/1947 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
    Vol. 1-6
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 10/1947 --05/1952 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
    Vol. 7-11
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 10/1950 --05/1952 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
    Vol. 9-11
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 10/1952 --05/1955 (Box 1A, Folder 4)
    Vol. 12-14
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1954-1956 (Box 1A, Folder 10)
    General
    Volumes 14 and 15. Presentation copy given by M. Michael Brady, editor of Mecheleciv 1955-1956.
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 10/1955 --05/1957 (Box Box 1B, Folder 5)
    Vol. 15-16; 2 copies
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 10/1957 --05/1960 (Box Box 1B, Folder 6)
    Vol. 17-18
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 10/1960 --05/1962 (Box Box 1B, Folder 7)
    Vol. 19-20
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 10/1962 --05/1967 (Box 1C, Folder 8)
    Vol. 21-25
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 10/1967 --03/1972 (Box 1C, Folder 9)
    Vol. 26-29
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 03/1947 --03/1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Second copies; March 1947, May 1947, January 1948, October 1949, November 1949, December 1949, March 1950, April 1950, May 1950, December 1950, October 1952, December 1953, October 1956, October 1967, April 1968, March 1969
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 10/1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 09/1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Vol. 30:1
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 02/1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Vol. 30:2; 2 copies
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 11/1983 --12/1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Vol. 30:3
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Vol. 31:1; Spring issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine policies and procedures, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Summer
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Vol. 31:2; Fall issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Vol. 31:3; Fall issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Vol. 32:1; Spring issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Vol. 32:2; Spring issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Vol. 32:3; Fall issue, 2 copies
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Vol. 32:4; Fall issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Vol. 33:1; Spring issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Vol. 33:2; Spring issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Vol. 33:3; Fall issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Vol. 33:4; Fall issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Vol. 34:1; Spring issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Vol. 34:2; Summer issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Vol. 34:3; Fall issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Vol. 34:4; Winter issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Vol. 35:1; Spring issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Vol. 35:3; Fall issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Vol. 35:4; Winter issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Vol. 36:1; Spring issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Vol. 36:2; Fall issue
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Vol. 37:1; Winter issue
  - Mecheleciv newspaper, 11/04/1991 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Mecheleciv magazine, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Vol. 38:1; 2 copies of Spring "re-founding" issue
  - The Mecheleciv, Gap between 1971 and 1983; Series 7 (Box 1)
    Vol. 20 No. 1-2 Vol. 21 No. 1-4 Vol. 24 May 1966 No. 6 Vol. 25 No. 4, 6 Vol. 26 No. 1-6 Vol. 27 No. 1-6 Vol. 28 No. 1-6 Vol. 29 No. 1-4 Vol. 30 No. 3 Vol. 31 No. 1-2 Vol. 32 No. 1-4 Vol. 33 No. 1-3 Vol. 34 No. 1-4 Vol. 35 No. 1, 3, 4 Vol. 36 No. 1-2 Vol. 37 No. 1 Vol. 38 No. 1 Vol. 39 No. 1
- Publications and AV materials, RG0012 Series 8
  - Mechleciv magazines, photographs and contact sheets, 1969-2009 (Box 1)
    - SWE Magazine of the Society of Women Engineers, 2009
    - School of Engineering & Applied Science VHS tape
    - Synergy magazine, School of Engineering & Applied Science 125th Anniversary, 2009
      2 copies
    - Research & Diversity magazine, 2008
      Fall 2008.
    - GW Medical & Health magazine, 2009
      Summer 2009.
    - School of Engineering and Applied Science, The George Washington University
      Undated brochuere with photographs of school and program inside.
    - Unidentified photographs
      2 Manila folders full of photographs and negatives. Unidentified and no dates.
    - DVD & CD-R
      Mix of DVDs and CD-Rs. Total of 10 disks. Acceleglove demo video FHWA/NHTSA National Crash Analysis Center School of Engineering and Applied Science Graduate Programs. CNN The Flip Side.
  - SEAS publications, photographs and files, 1955-2008 (Box 2)
    - Engineering Innovations, Ongoing Research at the GW School of Engineering and Applied Science
      7 copies of the publication.
    - The Mecheleciv, 1967-1997
      Vol 26-39 incomplete set but there are multiple copies of the same issue. Vol. 26 No. 1-3 Vol. 27 No. 1-3 Vol. 28 No. 3-5 Vol. 29 No. 1, 2, 4 Vol. 30 No. 2, 3 Vol. 31 No. 1-3 Vol. 32 No. 1-4 Vol. 33 No. 1, 2, 4 Vol. 34 No. 1, 3, 4 Vol. 35 No. 1, 3, 4 Vol. 36 No. 2 Vol. 37 No. 1 Vol. 38 No. 1 Vol. 39 No. 1
    - School of Engineering and Applied Science history and brochures
      Includes document on history of SEAS and program.
    - The University Honors Program Handbook, 1996-1997
    - Solar Powered Car, Sunforce 1, 1993
    - Synergy newsletter, 2001
      Multiple copies of newsletter. Spring 2001 Vol. 1, Number 1 Winter 2001 Vol. 1, Number 2
    - GW Research magazine, 2005
      Multiple copies of magazine. Fall 2005.
    - Unidentified photographs
      Photographs are both portraits and action shots of various events in the School of Engineering and Applied Science.
    - CDs, 2003-2007
      10 disks total. Compact disks contain pictures and short videos.
    - Vault for the Future Tompkins Hall of Engineering, 1955-1956
      Notes, letters, and carbon copies regarding the Tompkins Hall of Engineering.
  - Photographs, 1986-1995 (Box 3)
    - Photographs, 1971
      Photographs are not in folders or have an order.
    - Photographs Engineering Management 1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Photographs 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - NASA (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Photographs: Concrete Canoe 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Special Projects Concrete Canoe, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Photographs 90, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Photos Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Photographs 1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - PERS/DEAN Profile '84, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Photographs 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Photographs, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Photos Intelligent Systems & Human Computer: 1993 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Honors '91-'92, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Photographs 1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Photographs 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Malaysia/Thailand/Taiwan Trip 1996 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Centuries Campaign Slides/Photos Borrowed and Returned June 6, 1996, 1996-06-06 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Tompkins Hall 1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Lectures Spring 1996 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Nahid Khozeimeh (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Photographs 1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Photographs '87, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Photographs 1986 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Enrollment F2002 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Photographs 1964 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Photographs 1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Photographs 1956 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Photographs 1981 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - 125th Anniversary History Article, 1943-2009 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - A/V materials and Solar Car proposals, 1997-2003 (Box 4)
    - Solar Car Project Completed Expense Forms, 1997
      Binder is full of expense reports, purchase requests, payment requests, and corresponding receipts.
    - Unidentified SEAS Photographs, 1999-2000
    - Engineering Innovations, Ongoing Research at the GW School of Engineering and Applied Science
      7 copies of publication.
    - VHS tapes, 2003-2005
      6 VHS tapes and 2 Sony DVCAM tapes. Each tape contains different footage regarding engineering and science. STS 114 PostFlight Presentation "Camarda Mission" 7/2005 USA Swimming - Rajat Mittal Science World Accreglove WTTG Fox 5 Story on Bridge Repairs w/ SEAS Professor Kim Roddis 6/30/05
    - E-Synergy newsletter
      E-synergy newsletter for the School of Engineering and Applied Science. Multiple copies of: Vol. 1 Iss. 1,2 Vol. 2 Iss. 2 Vol. 3 Iss. 1,2
    - Solar Car Project, 1997 Proposal
    - DVDs
      33 Discs with various information about the SEAS or School of Engineering and Applied Science.